<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: People | Pradeep Mishra]]></title>
  <link href="http://pkmishra.github.io/blog/categories/people/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://pkmishra.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-10-09T12:14:10+05:30</updated>
  <id>http://pkmishra.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Pradeep Kumar Mishra]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Technology as Fashion]]></title>
    <link href="http://pkmishra.github.io/blog/2013/10/09/technology-as-fashion/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-09T11:36:00+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://pkmishra.github.io/blog/2013/10/09/technology-as-fashion</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In today&rsquo;s world we are fortunate enough to have so many technologies, frameworks, open source projects to help us focus on solving business problem and build great product. There are certainly more than one option to solve the problem so which one should you select?</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>My belief is that technology should be selected based on the business problem you are trying to solve and not the other way round where bunch of enthusiast have decided to use new technology and thereafter trying to fit what all problems can be solved using that technology. This certainly can not be in the best interest of the organization. I am not against innovation or experimenting with new set of technologies but one should not use new set of technologies because one wants to add new set of keywords in your resume. One should also think about other cost e.g. maintenance, support and hiring. Let&rsquo;s look at some real world examples…</p>

<ol>
<li> In an organization cakePHP framework is used for 2 applications now you hired a new manager who is comfortable in codeIgniter so for new application he selects codeIgniter. Later you hired another bright guy who likes to work in Laravel4 so Laravel was selected and so on. I have seen similar things for other javascript frameworks as well.</li>
<li> Another example is buzzword BigData. Big data is in fashion today people who are dealing with 500GB of data talk about using nosql solutions without having full understanding.  Chris has summarized this in his blog nicely.  Another example is worrying too much about scalability at the initial phase itself instead of making product valuable enough for the end user. Sometime it is good to cross the bridge when it comes.</li>
</ol>


<p>So what are the factors which affects technology selection?
There are no set rules but one rule must be taken care of i.e. Solve the business problem by using right set of technologies. Few other points I can think of are</p>

<ol>
<li> What is the technology vision of the company? If you are just supporting legacy system for some time and would like to move on to new product all together definitely you should explore usage of newer and widely accepted framework.</li>
<li> Talent and Knowledge &ndash; The most important asset of any organization is people therefore if you already have experts in some area why not optimize that. e.g. If you already have rockstars in Python there is no need to develop app in PHP or in Asp.Net. Productivity will also be very high in this case.</li>
<li> Attracting new Talent &ndash;  If you are using very new technology you might not find good talent but again if your business problem require to built a new high concurrent system and you already have java guys one should definitely try Scala/GoLang for new products.</li>
<li> Build smarter tool &ndash; When Facebook faced issues with php scalability they didn&rsquo;t migrate the whole code to different tech stack rather they created a new tool hiphop which compiles code into C++. Every company doesn&rsquo;t have luxury of very smart talent like Facebook but still some work around can be explored depending upon the situation.</li>
</ol>


<p>So in a big organization who should be accountable for technology convergence?
Depending upon organization size CTO/Chief Architect/VP Engineering is the person where buck stops. He/She should make sure that whatever technology/frameworks engineers are using are solving business problem and are not there just because the new technology is in vogue.</p>

<p>Comments/Feedbacks are welcome.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
